<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: music | JP Simard]]></title>
  <link href="https://jpsim.com/categories/music/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://jpsim.com/"/>
  <updated>2018-05-20T15:13:59+10:00</updated>
  <id>https://jpsim.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[JP Simard]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[jp@jpsim.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Goals for <span>2013</span>]]></title>
    <link href="https://jpsim.com/goals-for-2013/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-07T12:03:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>https://jpsim.com/goals-for-2013</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Writing my goals for 2013 publicly to keep myself accountable.</p>

<h2>Gig monthly</h2>

<h3>What?</h3>

<p>There was a time when I played sax at local restaurants, corporate gigs, heck I even <a href="http://mgn.tc/psgroove">recorded an album</a> with <a href="http://patricksimard.com">my brother</a> that sold pretty decently.</p>

<h3>How?</h3>

<p>I've got a bassist, drummer and guitarist lined up. I'm approaching several of the bars/restaurants I used to play to set up some gigs.</p>

<h2>Learn Japanese</h2>

<h3>What?</h3>

<p><a href="http://twitter.com/c_contant">Christine</a> and I will be learning Japanese this year. Our goal is to reach survival-in-Japan level by the end of the year.</p>

<h3>How?</h3>

<p>I bought all 3 levels of Rosetta Stone Japanese today. 3x 20 minutes and an hour-long session with Christine once a week.</p>

<h2>Get featured on Hacker News</h2>

<h3>What?</h3>

<p>I'd certainly like to refine my writing abilities and this is a stretch goal to accomplish that.</p>

<h3>How?</h3>

<p>Blogging here and on the <a href="http://magneticbear.com/labs">MBS Labs</a> website weekly.</p>

<h2>Run a 3:30 marathon</h2>

<h3>What?</h3>

<p>I'm not in the shape I'd like to be. I ran a 4:00 marathon last year and I can already run a 1:30 half marathon so this is the next logical step.</p>

<h3>How?</h3>

<p>Following the <a href="http://runkeeper.com/fitness-class/running-marathon/12">RunKeeper training plan</a>. Track my progress on my <a href="http://runkeeper.com/user/jpsim/profile">RunKeeper profile</a>.</p>

<h2>Bike daily</h2>

<h3>What?</h3>

<p>Starting on February 1st (in the snow for an added challenge). This doesn't apply to days I have to drive.</p>

<h3>How?</h3>

<p>I'm buying a bike and doing it!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
