<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: cloudformation | JP Simard]]></title>
  <link href="https://jpsim.com/categories/cloudformation/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://jpsim.com/"/>
  <updated>2018-11-22T17:10:01-08:00</updated>
  <id>https://jpsim.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[JP Simard]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[jp@jpsim.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Building a serverless password-protected photo gallery]]></title>
    <link href="https://jpsim.com/awspics/"/>
    <updated>2017-07-04T06:14:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>https://jpsim.com/awspics</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Building a serverless photo gallery?
<em>Easy!</em>
Password-protecting that without adding servers?
<em>Surprisingly much more complex.</em></p>

<p><img src="https://github.com/jpsim/AWSPics/raw/master/assets/awspics.gif" alt="" /></p>

<h2>Goals</h2>

<blockquote><p>Host a self-contained, declarative infrastructure, password-protected,
data-driven static photo gallery to share personal pictures with friends and
family, without needing to run, maintain (or pay for) servers.</p></blockquote>

<p>With <a href="https://twitter.com/simjp/status/873604866043543552">the recent addition</a>
to our family, I wanted to set up a place where I could share pictures with
our closest friends and family. Facebook wasn't an option because...
<a href="https://daringfireball.net/2017/06/fuck_facebook">yeah</a>,
<a href="http://www.slate.com/articles/technology/data_mine_1/2013/09/facebook_privacy_and_kids_don_t_post_photos_of_your_kids_online.html">because</a>
<a href="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/women/family/i-dont-put-pictures-of-my-children-on-facebook---and-you-shouldn/">many</a>
<a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com.au/2016/02/07/can-i-post-photos-of-other-peoples-children_n_9184560.html">reasons</a>
<a href="https://medium.com/matter/beware-your-baby-s-face-is-online-and-on-sale-d33ae8cdaa9d">actually</a>.</p>

<p>Most of my family members are on Apple devices, while most of my friends are in
the Google/Android ecosystem. So for day to day sharing of moments, we post a
few pictures to iCloud photo sharing, and a few others to a WhatsApp group. But
neither of these can really serve as the canonical place where we're storing
these photos long-term, because WhatsApp is pretty ephemeral, and the iCloud
photo sharing experience <em>sucks</em> on non-Apple devices.</p>

<h2>Architecture</h2>

<p>Unfortunately there's no "put a password in front of AWS CloudFront" checkbox.
I wish there were, so I wouldn't have had to build this. But there isn't, so it
was time to roll up my sleeves and learn a bit about how modern web
infrastructure is built. Or at least my idea of it.</p>

<p><img src="https://github.com/jpsim/AWSPics/raw/master/assets/architecture.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>There are 7 main components:</p>

<ol>
<li><strong>CloudFront with restricted bucket access</strong> to prevent unauthenticated
access to the site or its pictures.</li>
<li><strong>Login lambda function</strong> to validate authentication and sign cookies to
allow access to restricted buckets.</li>
<li><strong>Source S3 bucket</strong> to store original pictures and metadata driving the
site.</li>
<li><strong>Resized S3 bucket</strong> to store resized versions of the original pictures.</li>
<li><strong>Web S3 bucket</strong> to store the static website generated from the data in the
source bucket.</li>
<li><strong>Resize lambda function</strong> to automatically resize images added to the source
S3 bucket and store them in the resized S3 bucket.</li>
<li><strong>Site builder lambda function</strong> to automatically rebuild the static website
when changes are made to the source S3 bucket.</li>
</ol>


<h2>Can it be simplified?</h2>

<p>Of course. There are a few ways I can think of to simplify this, but the
tradeoffs aren't worthwhile IMO.</p>

<ol>
<li><strong>Resize images on demand.</strong> Rather than resize all the images when they're
first added to the source bucket, the resize lambda could be exposed via a
CloudFront origin. However, since the static site only really uses two
image sizes, and that lambda functions have a significant
<a href="https://serverless.com/blog/keep-your-lambdas-warm/">cold start penalty</a>,
it's much more efficient to just precompute the resized images.</li>
<li><strong>Consolidate buckets.</strong>  Rather than separate source, resized &amp; web buckets,
they could just be in a single bucket. However, this would just shift the
complexity a bit since the stack would then need to filter new object
notifications to know which function to invoke. Plus, right now to back up
the valuable content, I just need to periodically mirror the source bucket,
rather than all the derivative data in the resized and web buckets.</li>
</ol>


<h2>Problems?</h2>

<p>I have a few annoyances with this setup as-is.</p>

<p>One is that only the resized bucket triggers the site builder function. That
means that any other object modified in the source bucket, such as the
<code>metadata.yml</code> files that include album comments, don't trigger a site build.</p>

<p>Another related problem is that for every new image in the source bucket, two
are created in the resized bucket, each one invoking the site builder function.
Not only that, but if I upload an album with lots of pictures all in one shot,
the site will be rebuilt twice for each picture! 🙀</p>

<p>Unfortunately, S3 buckets can only have a
<a href="https://stackoverflow.com/q/31471178/373262">single notification per event type</a>,
so we can't trigger both the resize and site builder functions when new objects
are created on the source bucket.</p>

<p>I think the solution here would involve
<a href="http://docs.aws.amazon.com/AmazonS3/latest/dev/NotificationHowTo.html">publishing S3 events to SNS or SQS</a>
and "debouncing" the site builder lambda, but again... <strong>#complexity</strong>.</p>

<p><img src="https://media.giphy.com/media/mYqaRkXyoGbcY/giphy.gif" alt="" /></p>

<p>I'll probably do this eventually, but I'm in no hurry.</p>

<h2>Code</h2>

<p>I've open sourced the entire AWS stack on GitHub over at
<a href="https://github.com/jpsim/AWSPics">jpsim/AWSPics</a>. I'm also hosting a demo
site over at <a href="https://awspics.net">awspics.net</a> (use "username"/"password" as
credentials to check it out).</p>

<p>There's a (long) video walkthrough <a href="https://youtu.be/010AGcY4uoE">on YouTube</a>
too, if that's useful to follow along.</p>

<h2>Closing Thoughts</h2>

<p>Overall, I really enjoyed stepping outside my comfort zone of native
Swift/ObjC/C++ programming, learning a TON about several AWS services and
ultimately meeting my goal of setting up a private photo gallery.</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">If you think incremental Xcode builds take a while, try deploying changes to an AWS CloudFormation stack 😅 <a href="https://t.co/yTPsqarT92">pic.twitter.com/yTPsqarT92</a></p>&mdash; JP Simard (@simjp) <a href="https://twitter.com/simjp/status/881640404851884033">July 2, 2017</a></blockquote>


<script async src="https://jpsim.com//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
