<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: development | JP Simard]]></title>
  <link href="http://jpsim.github.com/categories/development/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jpsim.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2018-05-12T17:01:23-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://jpsim.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[JP Simard]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[jp@jpsim.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Building a serverless password-protected photo gallery]]></title>
    <link href="http://jpsim.github.com/awspics/"/>
    <updated>2017-07-04T06:14:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jpsim.github.com/awspics</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Building a serverless photo gallery?
<em>Easy!</em>
Password-protecting that without adding servers?
<em>Surprisingly much more complex.</em></p>

<p><img src="https://github.com/jpsim/AWSPics/raw/master/assets/awspics.gif" alt="" /></p>

<h2>Goals</h2>

<blockquote><p>Host a self-contained, declarative infrastructure, password-protected,
data-driven static photo gallery to share personal pictures with friends and
family, without needing to run, maintain (or pay for) servers.</p></blockquote>

<p>With <a href="https://twitter.com/simjp/status/873604866043543552">the recent addition</a>
to our family, I wanted to set up a place where I could share pictures with
our closest friends and family. Facebook wasn't an option because...
<a href="https://daringfireball.net/2017/06/fuck_facebook">yeah</a>,
<a href="http://www.slate.com/articles/technology/data_mine_1/2013/09/facebook_privacy_and_kids_don_t_post_photos_of_your_kids_online.html">because</a>
<a href="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/women/family/i-dont-put-pictures-of-my-children-on-facebook---and-you-shouldn/">many</a>
<a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com.au/2016/02/07/can-i-post-photos-of-other-peoples-children_n_9184560.html">reasons</a>
<a href="https://medium.com/matter/beware-your-baby-s-face-is-online-and-on-sale-d33ae8cdaa9d">actually</a>.</p>

<p>Most of my family members are on Apple devices, while most of my friends are in
the Google/Android ecosystem. So for day to day sharing of moments, we post a
few pictures to iCloud photo sharing, and a few others to a WhatsApp group. But
neither of these can really serve as the canonical place where we're storing
these photos long-term, because WhatsApp is pretty ephemeral, and the iCloud
photo sharing experience <em>sucks</em> on non-Apple devices.</p>

<h2>Architecture</h2>

<p>Unfortunately there's no "put a password in front of AWS CloudFront" checkbox.
I wish there were, so I wouldn't have had to build this. But there isn't, so it
was time to roll up my sleeves and learn a bit about how modern web
infrastructure is built. Or at least my idea of it.</p>

<p><img src="https://github.com/jpsim/AWSPics/raw/master/assets/architecture.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>There are 7 main components:</p>

<ol>
<li><strong>CloudFront with restricted bucket access</strong> to prevent unauthenticated
access to the site or its pictures.</li>
<li><strong>Login lambda function</strong> to validate authentication and sign cookies to
allow access to restricted buckets.</li>
<li><strong>Source S3 bucket</strong> to store original pictures and metadata driving the
site.</li>
<li><strong>Resized S3 bucket</strong> to store resized versions of the original pictures.</li>
<li><strong>Web S3 bucket</strong> to store the static website generated from the data in the
source bucket.</li>
<li><strong>Resize lambda function</strong> to automatically resize images added to the source
S3 bucket and store them in the resized S3 bucket.</li>
<li><strong>Site builder lambda function</strong> to automatically rebuild the static website
when changes are made to the source S3 bucket.</li>
</ol>


<h2>Can it be simplified?</h2>

<p>Of course. There are a few ways I can think of to simplify this, but the
tradeoffs aren't worthwhile IMO.</p>

<ol>
<li><strong>Resize images on demand.</strong> Rather than resize all the images when they're
first added to the source bucket, the resize lambda could be exposed via a
CloudFront origin. However, since the static site only really uses two
image sizes, and that lambda functions have a significant
<a href="https://serverless.com/blog/keep-your-lambdas-warm/">cold start penalty</a>,
it's much more efficient to just precompute the resized images.</li>
<li><strong>Consolidate buckets.</strong>  Rather than separate source, resized &amp; web buckets,
they could just be in a single bucket. However, this would just shift the
complexity a bit since the stack would then need to filter new object
notifications to know which function to invoke. Plus, right now to back up
the valuable content, I just need to periodically mirror the source bucket,
rather than all the derivative data in the resized and web buckets.</li>
</ol>


<h2>Problems?</h2>

<p>I have a few annoyances with this setup as-is.</p>

<p>One is that only the resized bucket triggers the site builder function. That
means that any other object modified in the source bucket, such as the
<code>metadata.yml</code> files that include album comments, don't trigger a site build.</p>

<p>Another related problem is that for every new image in the source bucket, two
are created in the resized bucket, each one invoking the site builder function.
Not only that, but if I upload an album with lots of pictures all in one shot,
the site will be rebuilt twice for each picture! 🙀</p>

<p>Unfortunately, S3 buckets can only have a
<a href="https://stackoverflow.com/q/31471178/373262">single notification per event type</a>,
so we can't trigger both the resize and site builder functions when new objects
are created on the source bucket.</p>

<p>I think the solution here would involve
<a href="http://docs.aws.amazon.com/AmazonS3/latest/dev/NotificationHowTo.html">publishing S3 events to SNS or SQS</a>
and "debouncing" the site builder lambda, but again... <strong>#complexity</strong>.</p>

<p><img src="https://media.giphy.com/media/mYqaRkXyoGbcY/giphy.gif" alt="" /></p>

<p>I'll probably do this eventually, but I'm in no hurry.</p>

<h2>Code</h2>

<p>I've open sourced the entire AWS stack on GitHub over at
<a href="https://github.com/jpsim/AWSPics">jpsim/AWSPics</a>. I'm also hosting a demo
site over at <a href="https://awspics.net">awspics.net</a> (use "username"/"password" as
credentials to check it out).</p>

<p>There's a (long) video walkthrough <a href="https://youtu.be/010AGcY4uoE">on YouTube</a>
too, if that's useful to follow along.</p>

<h2>Closing Thoughts</h2>

<p>Overall, I really enjoyed stepping outside my comfort zone of native
Swift/ObjC/C++ programming, learning a TON about several AWS services and
ultimately meeting my goal of setting up a private photo gallery.</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">If you think incremental Xcode builds take a while, try deploying changes to an AWS CloudFormation stack 😅 <a href="https://t.co/yTPsqarT92">pic.twitter.com/yTPsqarT92</a></p>&mdash; JP Simard (@simjp) <a href="https://twitter.com/simjp/status/881640404851884033">July 2, 2017</a></blockquote>


<script async src="http://jpsim.github.com//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Uncovering SourceKit]]></title>
    <link href="http://jpsim.github.com/uncovering-sourcekit/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-06T16:07:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jpsim.github.com/uncovering-sourcekit</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>To support a <a href="http://developer.apple.com/swift">fancy new language</a>, nifty <a href="https://developer.apple.com/library/prerelease/ios/recipes/xcode_help-source_editor/ExploringandEvaluatingSwiftCodeinaPlayground/ExploringandEvaluatingSwiftCodeinaPlayground.html">realtime IDE</a> features and impressive <a href="https://developer.apple.com/library/prerelease/ios/documentation/Swift/Conceptual/BuildingCocoaApps/InteractingWithObjective-CAPIs.html">cross-language interoperability</a>, Apple had to develop several new underlying tools. Here, we'll focus on <em>SourceKit</em>, Xcode's under-appreciated sidekick.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/sidekick.jpg" alt="sidekick" /></p>

<center><sub>SourceKitSidekick temporarily wearing a cape</sub></center>


<p><br/></p>

<h2>What is SourceKit?</h2>

<p>SourceKit is the set of tools that enables most of Swift's source code manipulation features: source code parsing, syntax highlighting, typesetting, autocomplete, cross-language header generation, and lots more.</p>

<h2>Architecture</h2>

<p>Xcode traditionally runs its compiler (<a href="http://clang.llvm.org">Clang</a>) <em>in-process</em>, which means that any time the compiler would crash, so would the IDE.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/house_of_cards.jpg" alt="house of cards" /></p>

<center><sub>Xcode architecture diagram</sub></center>


<p><br/></p>

<p>Exacerbating the problem, Xcode can easily invoke the compiler thousands of times to parse, highlight and typeset source code, all before a user ever hits <em>⌘+B</em>. That's because unlike most editors (Vim/Sublime/etc), Xcode doesn't use regular expressions to parse source code, but rather Clang's powerful (though much more complex) parser/tokenizer.</p>

<p>Thankfully, Swift in Xcode 6 moves away from this architecture<sup>1</sup>, combining all these source code manipulation features into a separate process that communicates with Xcode through <a href="https://developer.apple.com/library/mac/documentation/macosx/conceptual/bpsystemstartup/chapters/CreatingXPCServices.html">XPC</a>: <code>sourcekitd</code>. This XPC daemon is launched whenever Xcode 6 loads any Swift code.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/sourcekit_terminated.jpg" alt="sourcekit terminated" /></p>

<center><sub>Life would be miserable if Xcode crashed every time this appeared</sub></center>


<p><br/></p>

<h2>How Xcode uses SourceKit</h2>

<p>Since SourceKit is a private and undocumented tool, we need to get a little creative to learn how to use it. By setting the <code>SOURCEKIT_LOGGING</code><sup>2</sup> environment variable, Xcode will log its SourceKit communications to <code>stdout</code>, allowing us to monitor its communications in realtime. This is how many of the commands covered in this article were discovered.</p>

<h2>Unified Symbol Resolution</h2>

<p>SourceKit uses a Clang feature called the USR (Unified Symbol Resolution) as a unique identifier for a source code token (i.e. class, property, method, etc.). This is what allows you to <em>⌘+click</em> any token in Xcode and navigate to its definition. The USR is even more powerful now that it can unify a representation across languages (Swift/ObjC).</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/usr.jpg" alt="usr" /></p>

<center><sub>The USR at work</sub></center>


<p><br/></p>

<p>To print the USR's from a Swift file (and their locations), you can run the following command:</p>

<pre><code>$ xcrun swift-ide-test -print-usrs -source-filename=Musician.swift
10:7 s:C14swift_ide_test8Musician
14:9 s:vC14swift_ide_test8Musician4nameSS
19:9 s:vC14swift_ide_test8Musician9birthyearSu
33:5 s:FC14swift_ide_test8MusiciancFMS0_FT4nameSS9birthyearSu_S0_
33:10 s:vFC14swift_ide_test8MusiciancFMS0_FT4nameSS9birthyearSu_S0_L_4nameSS
33:24 s:vFC14swift_ide_test8MusiciancFMS0_FT4nameSS9birthyearSu_S0_L_9birthyearSu
34:9 s:vFC14swift_ide_test8MusiciancFMS0_FT4nameSS9birthyearSu_S0_L_4selfS0_
34:21 s:vFC14swift_ide_test8MusiciancFMS0_FT4nameSS9birthyearSu_S0_L_4nameSS
35:9 s:vFC14swift_ide_test8MusiciancFMS0_FT4nameSS9birthyearSu_S0_L_4selfS0_
35:26 s:vFC14swift_ide_test8MusiciancFMS0_FT4nameSS9birthyearSu_S0_L_9birthyearSu
</code></pre>

<h2>Swift<em>ish</em> header generation</h2>

<p><em>⌘+clicking</em> on a token defined in Objective-C from Swift will cause Xcode to trigger a Swift-like header to be generated. I say Swift-like because this generated file is not valid Swift<sup>3</sup>, but at least displays the Swift syntax equivalent to the Objective-C tokens.</p>

<p><a href="/images/posts/generated_swift_header.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/generated_swift_header.jpg" alt="Generated Swift Header" /></a></p>

<center><sub>Left: original Objective-C header. Right: SourceKit-generated Swift-ish version.</sub></center>


<p><br/></p>

<h2>Using SourceKit from the command line</h2>

<p><img src="/images/posts/sourcekit_playground.jpg" alt="SourceKit Playground" /></p>

<p>There are 3 main command line tools that allow to interact with SourceKit: <code>sourcekitd-test</code>, <code>swift-ide-test</code> and <code>swift</code>.</p>

<p>I compiled a shell script with documentation that runs through many useful commands like syntax highlighting, interface generation, AST parsing, demangling, and more.</p>

<p>The script is available on GitHub as a <a href="https://gist.github.com/jpsim/13971c81445219db1c63#file-sourcekit_playground-sh">gist</a>.</p>

<h2>3rd Party Tools Using SourceKit</h2>

<p>Because SourceKit lives outside of Xcode, it’s possible to leverage it to build anything from a Swift IDE to a documentation generator.</p>

<h3>jazzy<sup>♪♫</sup></h3>

<p><img src="/images/posts/jazzy.jpg" alt="jazzy" /></p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/realm/jazzy">jazzy</a> is a command-line utility that generates documentation for your Swift and Objective-C projects. It uses SourceKit to derive Swift syntax from Objective-C defined tokens (i.e. class, property, method, etc.).</p>

<h3>SwiftEdit</h3>

<p><a href="https://github.com/jpsim/SwiftEdit">SwiftEdit</a> is a proof-of-concept editor that supports syntax highlighting for Swift files.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/SwiftEdit.png" alt="SwiftEdit" /></p>

<h2>SourceKit &amp; You</h2>

<p>We’re just scratching the surface of what’s possible to build with SourceKit. Tools could be made to measure cross-language code coverage, or provide an editor where Objective-C and Swift can be edited simultaneously. Hopefully this article inspires you to build something with SourceKit and improve our tools in the process.</p>

<hr />

<p><em>1: Objective-C in Xcode 6 (Beta 2) doesn't use SourceKit at all, keeping Xcode's traditional clang-in-process architecture. I expect this to change before Xcode 6 GM.</em></p>

<p><em>2: For SourceKit logging, launch Xcode with <sub><code>export SOURCEKIT_LOGGING=3 &amp;&amp; /Applications/Xcode6-Beta2.app/Contents/MacOS/Xcode</code></sub></em></p>

<p><em>3: Speculation: I expect private Swift modules to expose public interfaces using a similar syntax once the language has <a href="https://github.com/ksm/SwiftInFlux#access-control">access control mechanisms</a>.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SF Swift Meetup]]></title>
    <link href="http://jpsim.github.com/sf-swift-meetup/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-27T14:58:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jpsim.github.com/sf-swift-meetup</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I recently gave a talk on <a href="https://developer.apple.com/swift">Swift</a> at the <a href="http://www.meetup.com/swift-language">SF/SV Swift Language User Group</a> meetup. We've made the whole thing available online:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://realm.io/news/swift-unchartered-territory-swift-intro-and-internals">Video</a></li>
<li><a href="https://speakerdeck.com/jpsim/swift-uncharted-territory">Slides</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/jpsim/talks">Slides Source</a></li>
</ul>


<p>The first half of the talk covers the basic features and syntax of the language. The rest of the talk touches on some more in-depth discoveries about the runtime, introspection and how the tools work behind the scenes.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[JPSThumbnailAnnotation updated for iOS 7]]></title>
    <link href="http://jpsim.github.com/jpsthumbnailannotation-updated-for-ios-7/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-27T11:55:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jpsim.github.com/jpsthumbnailannotation-updated-for-ios-7</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I've just given a fresh coat of iOS7-flavoured paint to my most popular open-source library: JPSThumbnailAnnotation.</p>

<p>Check it out on <a href="https://github.com/jpsim/JPSThumbnailAnnotation">GitHub</a> or just add it to CocoaPods: <code>pod 'JPSThumbnailAnnotation'</code>.</p>

<p><img src="https://github.com/jpsim/JPSThumbnailAnnotation/raw/master/screenshots2.jpg" alt="Screenshots" /></p>

<p>I decided not to maintain the iOS 6 <em>style</em>, but iOS 6 is still supported.</p>

<p>By the way, this is what the old style looked like. It's still in git, if you need to find it for some reason.</p>

<p><img src="https://github.com/jpsim/JPSThumbnailAnnotation/raw/master/screenshots.jpg" alt="Old Screenshots" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Keyboard Layout Guide]]></title>
    <link href="http://jpsim.github.com/keyboard-layout-guide/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-26T14:41:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jpsim.github.com/keyboard-layout-guide</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I really like iOS 7's <code>topLayoutGuide</code> and <code>bottomLayoutGuide</code>. They're immensely useful. But in my adventures with Auto Layout, I've often wished that Apple had added a third member to this exclusive group: a sort of <code>keyboardLayoutGuide</code>.</p>

<p>It's a bit of a drag to have to set up <code>NSNotification</code> observers just to be able to keep your textfield on the screen when the keyboard barges into view. So I added a <code>keyboardLayoutGuide</code> to <code>UIViewController</code> myself. You can check it out on GitHub here: <a href="https://github.com/jpsim/JPSKeyboardLayoutGuide">jpsim/JPSKeyboardLayoutGuide</a>.</p>

<p>If you've used Apple's layout guides before, you'll know that they're actually just <code>id</code>'s that conform to the <a href="https://developer.apple.com/library/ios/documentation/uikit/reference/UILayoutSupport_Protocol/Reference/Reference.html"><code>UILayoutSupport</code> Protocol</a>. So I figured that having the guide just be a zero-sized UIView was probably the best way to go. This way, I can easily add it to the view and bind it to the keyboard frame by modifying a constraint's constant.</p>

<p>In all honesty, I dislike the inheritance approach I took here; it seems like the easy way out. I'm hoping that either myself or a contributor will have a stroke of genius and find a composition-based way to do this. Perhaps a starting point would be a category on <code>UIViewController</code> along with an associated object as the <code>keyboardLayoutGuide</code> property... But then the <code>NSNotification</code>s will be troublesome. If you have an idea, please fork and send a PR or open up an issue on <a href="https://github.com/jpsim/JPSKeyboardLayoutGuide">github</a>!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
